so you once said um
that when you first came across
buddhism you would
meditate for an hour in the morning now
in the evening and keep the precepts you
keep the precepts um but then you were
kind of relaxed when it came to things
like sense restraints you might go out
with friends and um
yeah well even even then i would be
sense restrained i wouldn't go out and
then go wild or something but what i was
less about what i was not seeing
was like
why would i go out
why would i do things i wanted to do
there was within the precepts
and within my meditation routine per day
yeah but still why would i do these
things and it was clearly rooted in
central desire or distraction and so on
and i wasn't aware of that domain not at
the time
that was the issue there like the
intentions behind my actions
were covered up because i felt justified
that i'm fulfilling my duty by keeping
the precepts and meditating regularly so
the meditation was like a compensation
well yeah it gives you afterwards when i
started questioning my motivation
regardless of how dutiful i was that day
or not i realized well no but that's
what the problem is the buddha didn't
say well as long as you sit in the
morning and evening do your pujas and
chores it's fine to you know distract yourself
it's fine to you know distract yourself
as like no
he actually didn't make all these
external requirements of methods and
techniques because he said what the
problem is and if you stay there
everything else will fall into place so
if i were to instead
meditate in the evening meditating in
the morning for an hour and watch my
nostrils and everything else if instead
i just didn't do that but at the same
time did not act out of a desire to go
out and distract myself with wholesome
friends and then endure the discomfort of their
and then endure the discomfort of their
desire for three days if it lasts that's
my mindfulness that's my samadhi that
would have been the direct practice
they would have saved me ton of time
until i found out later on just through
trial and error basically
but if you don't want to admit that if
you don't want to face the
unpleasantness of
you know losing relationships or
practicing celibacy
then you see this this one hour in the
morning and one hour in the evening
that's very valuable because then you
can keeps you grounded yeah it keeps you
basically gives you uh gives you gives you makes
gives you uh gives you gives you makes
you able to justify what you know deep
down is a compromise
and that's why
again a person might be you know
not clear about it yet covering it up a
bit of course it's a mixture of both but
then if somebody were to point it out if
they were really honest they would say
they would say thank you
they would see the point
if they don't say thank you and if they
start to double down and try to justify
the method the technique that whatever
else compensation they're doing it's
like oh now they're fully aware actually
that it's it's all rooted in weakness in
a cover-up which is now this even more
habitual defense mechanism so it's like
a doubling down in like dishonesty
within yourself
because again
you read just
not even all the suitors just take a few
and you will see acting out of desire
acting out of greed aversion that's the
root of the problem
so
are you spending your time
of practice
by keeping an eye on whether you have
that in these things by body speech and
mind or is your practice projected onto
some sort of external level norm of
behavior routines techniques methods
observations so that you don't look at the intentions
so that you don't look at the intentions
behind your actions
so like there is a direct way that would
have to result in the right view and
liberation and that way is the way of
knowing where your intentions are and
not fueling them further
which is
yeah peripheral in the sense that a
technique i mean it is technique is
already rooted yeah in some sort of
intention that's making you do it if i'm
desperately trying to focus on my breath
or my sensations in my body
i i am craving there is a there is a
peripheral to that yeah as is is
peripheral to that is your
implicit design that it's making you
basically it's already making all of
your actions kind of giving them a
meaning whatever their meaning is so in
this case the meaning is well let me
just absorb myself in it because that's
where the knowledge is so i won't have
to deal
with that vast open space of you know
doubt discomfort and lack of clarity on
that mental level which is you know the
the worst feeling for somebody who's
avoiding it you can see why that would
be popular in the sense yeah because
it's more palpable more measurable and
also because it plays into already
existing cover-ups and dishonesty
but if you expect to understand your eye
simply on the on account of the objects
you're observing externally that will
never be what your eye is i is that
because of which there are sights
your consciousness can meet sights which
is an interesting retina through a
microscope exactly then they think oh
but if i look at someone else's eye i
learn about my eye i know you're
learning about the organ but you're not
learning about the eye faculty the eye
that actually is the basis for vision
and then let's see but now if you were
to even start to question that view for
yourself exactly you're going to meet
with this
thick impenetrable wall of ambiguous
what are my senses then this this
internal thing where i just get worked
and distorted and filled with anxiety
so what do i do well let me just call
myself and you know adopt a technique
set the strict rules and so on and look
look the buddha talks about vinnie all
the time so it's important yeah it's
important to be done rightly
but it's not a justification no i'll
just adhere to this so i won't have to
look at my intentions no you keep the
winner so that you can reveal your
attentions intentions even further but
that illusivity is
uncomfortable because exactly why is
then elusivity ambiguity a problem is it
because it's not clear or is it because
it's painful
also then you assume that clarity will
free you from pain so your pursuit for
clarity is simply rooted in craving
against pain nuts
nuts
and that feeds feeds your craving
further which means makes you liable to
pain further
ignoring this fundamental assumption
that pain is a problem
pain is a problem
exactly and and that
that problem problem of aversion to its
pain and uh
and uh
infatuation towards with pleasure is
it's it's
like at any given
level of your experience yeah it's not
like oh i need to uncover this so
somewhere it's not deeply buried it's
like at the front at the back it's
everywhere whatever you do that is the
guiding principle
so it's obvious you know the way if you
were to like stop and look at it
it's impossible
to have an intention like
in the past or in the future they did
not go through that framework they
wasn't guided by that phrase all
intentions are yeah rooted in a desire
not to suffer or
craving for pleasure craving against
pain and craving for indolence when it's
neither pleasure nor pain that's it
but that's the the root of the entire
universe but the buddha saw that
like not
not
trying to get rid of pain is
is where
freedom from suffering lies
because yes people who constantly give
in to their desires
and have means of satisfying them they
will not become aware of the problem and
pain of craving because they never allow
time for it to really come to the forth
for it for them to see it so the longer
you allow it the more familiar you can
become with it the more your lights then
you have other people who say okay see
that's the problem and then they start
saying no to everything so although
initially they might have been more
accurate by nottingham centrality they
went the other way and now all we're
doing saying no to everything just again
so they wouldn't have to feel the pain
they wouldn't have to feel the
discomfort they wouldn't have to feel
the doubt like in
like in
uh come on that point the
because what a lot of people say
actually is that
like well you know it's my attachment to such
well you know it's my attachment to such
and such a thing that is a problem if i
wasn't attached to such and such a thing
this experience wouldn't be
painful it wouldn't yeah that's that is
true in the in the broader sense that is
in the in the broader sense that is
correct yeah yeah
but then then
what the
it is correct but then what kind of you
end up sort of doing say okay well
attachment i'll just kind of have to
give up all of my objects of attachment
so then nothing will be painful for me
everything will be fine
um
kind of forgetting that the attachment
to
pleasure and pain is also an attack yeah
yeah exactly so it's only like a as i
said in the broadest sense that view is
correct but then how you go about it
so yeah you gave up some degree of
things and to that extent you won't be
bothered but fundamentally you're
attached to your sense organs
because you know it says monks because
you take what doesn't belong to you mara
can do what he wants what is it that
doesn't belong to you that you take
basically you're attached to eye nose
ear body tongue it's like oh okay so don't
body tongue it's like oh okay so don't
take it because that belongs to mara and
then you'll be free
but that's not something you can just
say no to that's where that you know
like the other extreme of renunciation
loses perspective you know yes you need
to renounce say big firm no to central
desires and engaging and acting out of
anger and irritation but
uh that in itself it's only like you
know part of the picture
but if you think that by saying then
cultivating the same blanket no
even to internal states then again you
overshot the mark that's why i keep
saying goes back too often like i remember
goes back too often like i remember
reading that you know he gets rid of the
unwholesome thoughts how well the buddha
says by not welcoming or delighting not
acting out of by being watchful and then
all the similes of how thoughts
disappear they try to pressure you try
to make your try to entice you to come
out like a jackal get turtle so it can
bite it
but if turtle doesn't
put its limbs out of the shell jackaloos
interests and leaves and that's how
these thoughts are destroyed and got rid
of
but usually the attitude is no no no to
everything and then no no no to my
thoughts and then double down to know
and then just complete loss of
perspective expecting a blanket no
blanket renunciation to work where
basically the renunciation doesn't apply you
the renunciation doesn't apply you
cannot simply renounce your senses
oh let me renounce these eyes because
they are not object
of your attention off your senses which
is what you can renounce i can renounce
looking at this instead of look at
something else
but i can't renounce eyes i just can't
for as long as they're here i can't deny
them and then sure enough yeah some
people thought oh well if only i don't
have if only i would not have eyes or
ears i'd be liberated
and they said yeah my my teacher teaches
not seeing forms with the eyes and not
hearing things with either that's the
liberation he said well you know
different in a blind or a deaf man
and then that culminates into that whole
yeah you're still attached to avoiding
pain in prolonged pleasure
and how can you renounce that you can
only train yourself out of it
if i were to kind of question the let's
say my meditation in
the morning in the evening
then you know it would mean
you know it would mean
like that i don't have this to
fall back on so therefore i would have
to really start giving up things that i
don't want to give up because
you know if there was no reason
if
you know there would be no reason to
kind of um
avoid it to not be doing the dharma
properly actually if there wasn't
something that you are afraid to well
and that's kind of the irony like you
genuinely want to do it properly
i know i did from the start
but because
like of that kind of
careless supposedly cover up you're not
doing it properly so you want to do it
properly but you're going about it the
wrong way and that's why you're not
doing it properly
and and like even let's say somebody um
and like even let's say somebody um
you know somebody points out look it's
it's the wrong way
but now like if i have to admit this
this might be the wrong way
you know i don't know if it's the case
for for everybody but um you know
that might mean that basically my whole
kind of
every with this community i'm part of
this thing i this teacher i follow
like everything that has come to almost
sort of define my life
i might have been
against that that might not might have
to drop to drop all of this that is
really a heart very difficult thing to
kind of face and the more you have
acquired down that path of sort of cover-up but
down that path of sort of cover-up but
supposedly practice yet just acquiring
more the harder it will then be to admit it
the harder it will then be to admit it
yeah the harder it will be to go back
and drop it
that's why it's not like acting out and
holding wrong views it's not a neutral
thing it is adding weight to the burden
that you're already carrying
and it will be harder and harder to drop
it yeah
and and that's the thing like when you do
and that's the thing like when you do
sort of
come up against this or if you if you at
least have like an inkling of it and
then you start admitting it to yourself
it's like this um
like i remember at one point my mind
going kind of almost sort of wanting to
say please help somebody tell me
what is what is the right thing and then
i realize well look look what you're
doing asking somebody else looking for
god basically yeah yeah an external
external sort of
point of clarity and authority yeah and
but then i was like that's the whole
point of course that's the whole point
you know you can't if i were to go this
way and rely on this way if i would
i can't be more sure
that won't make me more sure the only
way out
then is to not go out
there outside yeah there is exactly
that's the only way out is to admit that
there is no outside of this
yeah exactly
that's that's what boils down to